Surendra Kumar

Data Scientist | Google Cloud Certified - Professional Data Engineer | Problem Solver

Ahmedabad | +91 8610292768 | sur365@gmail.com

in linkedin.com/in/surendrakumar365/ • skumarlabs.github.io

SUMMARY

A Google Cloud Certified - Professional Data Engineer and experienced in Data Science for ~4 years, an excellent understanding of NLP techniques, web scraping, building end-to-end predictive models and deploying them on cloud platforms like GCP, AWS etc

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist

Jan 2018 - Current

Tatvic Analytics

Working as a Data Scientist, my domain includes predictive analytics focused towards remarketing, social media analysis and other applications of machine learning to increase the user engagement with the client's product and to develop machine learning powered enterprise solutions.

System Engineer

Oct 2015 - Dec 2017

Tata Consultancy Services Limited

Working as System Engineer in BFS domain, my role involved developing and maintaining solutions to gather, analyse client's data and generating insights and reports to help them better understand their customer.

Khas Apke Liye

Description:

A content-based recommendation engine to serve better & personalized news articles on the website of Jagran Hindi daily having 31M+ readers per month

- **Responsibilities:** Extracting data from newly published articles using CMS API
 - Training a content model on the corpus of Hindi articles & building user
 - Deploying the model on GCP for serving the recommendations as JSON

Achievements:

- Achieved >8.9% CTR with the highest being >15.0% on mobile devices
- Improved AvgSessionDuration by >5 minutes

PredictN For Remarketing

Description:

A Prediction SaaS platform which predicts qualified audience list for remarketing who carry the higher probability of conversion on your site within the next 'N' days

- **Responsibilities:** Extracting data from Google Analytics
 - Training a predictive model to generate the optimal list of audience
 - Deploying the model on Google Compute Engine for serving

Achievements:

- Improved CPL of insurance company AegonLife by >55% using this solution
- Improved CVR of Eureka Forbes by 30%. Details here
- Similar improvements were measured for one of the largest vehicle & health insurance company in India which used the solution to target only a specific segment of the audience to remarket instead of traditional remarketing approaches

Proficiency

Workflow

Visual Studio Code, Git, Docker. Remote Development on Linux

Machine Learning Librararies / Tools

TensorFlow, Keras, NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-

Learn, Catboost, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Google Analytics, PySpark, NLTK, Gensim, Stanford CoreNLP, RapidMiner

Google Cloud Platform

Compute Engine, App Engine, Kubernetes Engine, Cloud Functions, Datastore, Cloud Storage, Networking, Stackdriver, Dataflow, BigQuery, ML Engine

Python 3

Modular and efficient code writing abilty with really good debugging skills

Web Development

HTML, JavaScript, CSS, Flask, FastAPI

Database and Warehouse

BigQuery, DataStore, MySQL, MongoDB

Core Competencies

- Predictive Modeling
- Deep Learning
- Statistics
- Time Series Analysis
- Topic Modeling
- Web Scraping
- API development
- Google Cloud Platform
- Google Analytics
- Data Studio Reporting

Social Listening

Description:

This project involved social media analysis for a fashion brand and an online shopping giant to give insights into how their brand was perceived by their users

- **Responsibilities:** Extracting data using Twitter API and Play Store reviews scraping
 - Building performance metrics such as brand engagement with the users on social media, performing sentiment analysis and topic modeling on tweets/reviews to gather insight into what the responses were about
 - Preparing reports & dashboards for insights in Google Data Studio

Other Side Projects

TV Ad Analysis: Time-Series analysis using RNNs to assess the impact of ad spots

on target demographics & provide recommendations for ad spots

yielding max impact

Feature Attribution Analysis for Conversion:

Feature attribution analysis using Markov chain for our client's flights booking data involving analysis of the website features; then attributing success (Conversions & Revenue) to different features. Provided useful insights to the client like poor performing features, how to optimize UI etc

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science & Engineering

2011 - 2015

Harcourt Butler Technical University, Kanpur

An aggregate of 67.5%. Got exposed to various ethical hacking related activities and worked as lead in the technical team of the department as well.

Senior Secondary School Examination

2009 - 2010

Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalaya, Kanpur

An aggregate percentage of 80.2 in CBSE Board

Secondary School Examination

2007 - 2008

Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalaya, Kanpur

An aggregate percentage of 89.2 in CBSE Board

HACKATHON PARTICIPATION

- 12th rank in MakeMyTrip Data Science Challenge
- 25th rank in Caavo Vision Challenge
- 47th rank in Data Science Challenge on HackerEarth which involved classification of X-ray images
- 180th rank with AUC score 0.8478 on McKinsey Analytics Online Hackathon Healthcare Analytics

CERTIFICATIONS & COURSES

- Google Cloud Certified Professional Data Engineer
- Networking in Google Cloud Platform training at Google, Gurgaon on May 7, 2019 to May 8, 2019
- Machine Learning with Tensorflow on Google Cloud Platform by Google on Coursera
- Deep Learning A-Z: Hands-on Artificial Neural Networks on Udemy Inc
- Machine Learning A-Z: Hands-On Python & R In Data Science on Udemy Inc
- Building Spark applications on Safari Online
- Cyber Crime & Security A 12-day certification course organized in association with the Indian Cyber Army during 20 May - 2 June 2013

LANGUAGES KNOWN

- Proficient in written and verbal communication in English, Hindi
- Good understanding with the scripts of Kannada, Tamil and Malayalam